Guide to the Max A. Lauffer Papers, 1915-2013 UA.90.F99
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Correspondence, 1944-2004; I.
  - Chronological Files, 3.
    - Correspondence, 1951
      - Correspondence: T, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - Correspondence: W, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Correspondence: Y, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence, 1952
      - Correspondence: A, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 26)
      - Correspondence: B, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - Correspondence: C, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - Correspondence: D, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - Correspondence: E, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 30)
      - Correspondence: F, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - Correspondence: G, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 32)
      - Correspondence: H, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 33)
      - Correspondence: J, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - Correspondence: K, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 35)
      - Correspondence: L, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 36)
      - Correspondence: M, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 37)
      - Correspondence: N, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - Correspondence: P, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 39)
      - Correspondence: R, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 40)
      - Correspondence: S, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 41)
      - Correspondence: T, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 42)
      - Correspondence: V, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 43)
      - Correspondence: W, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Correspondence, 1954
      - Correspondence: H, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 45)
      - Correspondence: J, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 46)
      - Correspondence: K, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 47)
      - Correspondence: L, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 48)
      - Correspondence: M, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 49)
      - Correspondence: N, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 50)
      - Correspondence: O, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 51)
      - Correspondence: P, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 52)
      - Correspondence: R, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 53)
      - Correspondence: S, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 54)
      - Correspondence: W, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Correspondence, 1955
      - Correspondence: B, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 56)
      - Correspondence: C, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 57)
      - Correspondence: D, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 58)
      - Correspondence: E, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 59)
      - Correspondence: F, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 60)
      - Correspondence: G, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 61)
      - Correspondence: H, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 62)
      - Correspondence: I, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 63)
      - Correspondence: K, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 64)
      - Correspondence: L, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 65)
      - Correspondence: M, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 66)
      - Correspondence: N, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 67)
      - Correspondence: P, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 68)
      - Correspondence: R, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 69)
      - Correspondence: S, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 70)
      - Correspondence: V, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 71)
      - Correspondence: W, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Correspondence, 1956
      - Correspondence: A, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 73)
      - Correspondence: B, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 74)
      - Correspondence: C, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 75)
      - Correspondence: D, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 76)
      - Correspondence: E, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 77)
      - Correspondence: F, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 78)
      - Correspondence: G, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 79)
      - Correspondence: H, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 80)
      - Correspondence: K, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 81)
      - Correspondence: L, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 82)
      - Correspondence: M, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 83)
      - Correspondence: O, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 84)
      - Correspondence: P, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 85)
      - Correspondence: R, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 86)
      - Correspondence: S, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 87)
      - Correspondence: T, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 88)
      - Correspondence: U, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 89)
      - Correspondence: W, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - Correspondence, 1959
      - Correspondence: B, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 91)
      - Correspondence: E, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 92)
      - Correspondence: F, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 93)
      - Correspondence: G, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 94)
      - Correspondence: H, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 95)
      - Correspondence: M, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 96)
      - Correspondence: P, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 97)
      - Correspondence: R, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 98)
      - Correspondence: S, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 99)
    - Correspondence, 1960
      - Correspondence: E, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 100)
      - Correspondence: H, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 101)
      - Correspondence: K, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 102)
      - Correspondence: P, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 103)
      - Correspondence: Y, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 104)
    - Correspondence, 1961
      - Correspondence: B, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 105)
      - Correspondence: E, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 106)
      - Correspondence: F, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 107)
      - Correspondence: H, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 108)
      - Correspondence: M, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 109)
      - Correspondence: N, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 110)
      - Correspondence: W, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 111)
  - Organizations, 1945-1991; 4.
    This subseries consists of Lauffer's correspondence with various professional and government organizations and groups. It is arranged alphabetically by the name of the organization.
    - American Chemical Society- Eli Lilly Award Committee, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - American Chemical Society- Lecture Tour, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - American Chemical Society- Lecture Tour, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - American Chemical Society- Lecture Tour, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - American Chemical Society- Lecture Tour, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - American Chemical Society- Pittsburgh Award, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - American Chemical Society, 1982, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - American Society of Biological Chemists, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Atomic Energy Commission, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Atomic Energy Commission, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Atomic Energy Commission, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Atomic Energy Commission, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Atomic Energy Commission, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Atomic Energy Commission, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Atomic Energy Commission, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Atomic Energy Commission, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Atomic Energy Commission, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Atomic Energy Commission, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Atomic Energy Commission, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Biological & Health Sciences at Pitt, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - The Biophysical Journal, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Boyce Thompson Institute for Plant Research, Inc., 1967-1983 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Chemical Warface Service- J.B. Bateman, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Chemical Warface Service- J.B. Bateman, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Chemical Warface Service- J.B. Bateman, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Chemical Warface Service- J.B. Bateman, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Chemical Warface Service- Leslie Chambers, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Chemical Warface Service- Leslie Chambers, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Chemical Warface Service- Leslie Chambers, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Chemical Warface Service- Camp Detrick Secretary, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Chemical Warface Service- Camp Detrick Secretary, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Committee on Medical Research, 1944-1946 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Federation of American Scientists, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Lilly Research Laboratories, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Lilly Research Laboratories, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Lilly Research Laboratories, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Lilly Research Laboratories, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Marine Biological Laboratory, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Middle States Association, 1984, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Municipal Hospital, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - New York Academy of Sciences, 1958-1959 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - New York Academy of Sciences, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - National Institutes of Health, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - NIH Special Study Section: To review application of Gilbert N. Ling, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - National Museum of American History, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - National Science Foundation, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - National Science Foundation, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - National Science Foundation, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - National Science Foundation, 1955-1957 (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - National Science Foundation Program Report, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - National Science Foundation Program Report, 1954-1955 (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - Office of Naval Research, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Office of Naval Research, 1952-1953 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Office of Naval Research, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Office of Naval Research, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - Office of Naval Research, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - Office of Naval Research, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Office of Naval Research, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - Office of Naval Research, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - Office of Naval Research, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Office of Naval Research, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Phipps Conservatory, Virus Research Program, 1945-1975 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Research in the Natural Sciences, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Research in the Natural Sciences, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Research in the Natural Sciences, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Research in the Natural Sciences, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Rockefeller University, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Scaife Foundation, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Scaife Foundation, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Scaife Foundation, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Scaife Foundation, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Scaife Foundation, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - U.S. Public Health Service, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - U.S. Public Health Service, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - U.S. Public Health Service, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - U.S. Public Health Service, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - U.S. Public Health Service, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - U.S. Public Health Service, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - U.S. Public Health Service, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - U.S. Public Health Service, National Institute of Health, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - U.S. Public Health Service, National Institute of Health, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - U.S. Public Health Service, National Institute of Health, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - United World Federalists, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Professional, 1944-2000; 5.
    This subseries consists of Lauffer's professional correspondence that is not directed to a specific individual or organization. The majority of this subseries consists of letters regarding manuscripts for his articles, but Cold War era "red scare" material and information for various university departments are also included.
    - Advances in Virus Research Series, 1953-1984 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Regarding Tobacco Mosaic Virus, 1969-1974 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - "Entropy-Driven Processes in Biology," Chapter 1, 1966-1974 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - "Entropy-Driven Process in Biology", 1974-1977 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - "Scanning Calometric Investigation of Polymerization of the Coat Protein of TMV," Biochemistry Vol. 20, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Motion in Biological Systems, 1988-1990 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - "Half a century with TMV and biophysics", 1996-2000 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Manuscripts, 1959-1963 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Manuscripts, 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Manuscripts, 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Manuscripts, 1968-1969 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Manuscripts, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Manuscripts, 1972-1979 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Manuscripts, 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Manuscripts, 1982-1985 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Herman T. Epstein & Loyalty Oath, 1949-1950, 1952-1953 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Loyalty Oath, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - McCarthy Era & Pennsylvania Loyalty Oaths, 1952-1953 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Confidential Edward Gerjuoy File, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Erdem Cantekin Dispute Re: Scientific Misconduct, 1990-1991 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Camp Detrick, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Camp Detrick, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Camp Detrick, 1963-1967 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Department of Physics, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - College of Arts and Sciences, 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Department of Political Science, 1983-1984 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Office of the Provost, 1983-1986 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Conference Participation, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Andrew W. Mellon Professorship, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Ross Aiken Gortner Fellowship, University of Minnesota, 1996-1998 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Impersonal, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Assorted Professional, 1951-1994 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Personal, 1948-2004; 6.
    This subseries consists of Lauffer's personal correspondence that are unrelated to his professional or scientific work. Included are letters related to religious activities, trips, and other letters to friends and colleagues. It is arranged chronologically.
    - European Trip, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Sabbatical in Tubingen, Germany, August 1965-April 1966 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Invitations, 1977, 1979, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Retirement Dinner, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - After Retirement, 1983-2004 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Assorted Personal, 1948-1993 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Personal, 1950s-1960s (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Personal, 1970s (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Personal, 1980s (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Personal, 1990s (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Personal (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - General, 1952-1988; 7.
    This subseries consists of correspondence that Lauffer had labeled as "general." It contains some letters concerning religion, but is primarily personal correspondence.
    - General-Religion, 1952-1987 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - General-Personal, 1956-1988 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - General, 1960s (Box 6, Folder 32-34)
    - General, 1960s (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - General, 1960s & 1970s (Box 7, Folder 2-4)
    - General, 1980s (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Talks and Lectures, 1938-2013; II.
  This series consists of copies of talks and lectures given by Lauffer over his career. Most talks are related to science and technical topics, though there are several that deal with religion and other subjects. Also included are speeches that he gave at various professional lecture series.
  - Scientific/Technical Lectures, 1938-1975; 1.
    This subseries consists of copies of lectures on scientific and technical topics that are arranged chronologically. There are also undated lectures placed at the end of the subseries.
    - Original Notes (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - List of Technical Lectures, 1938-1964 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Lectures in Biophysics and Molecular Biology, 1958-1959 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - "Electric Double Refraction of Viruses", March 4, 1940 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - "Bushy Stunt Virus", May 31, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - "Living Organisms", August 12, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - "Viruses: General", September 10, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - "The Rheology of Tobacco Mosaic Virus", October 24, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - "Viruses as Molecules: Crystalline Virus Protein", December 9, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - "Sedimentation Rate of the Infectious Principle of Tobacco Mosaic Virus", September 19, 1943 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - "Chemical and Physical Aspects of Virus Research", October 27, 1943, January 27, 1944 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - "Viruses", October 25, 1944 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - "Pathogenic Viruses and Fundamental Problems of Physics", March 14, 1945, May 3, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - "Outline: The Virus Research Program", September 25, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - "Dual Sedimentation Phenomenon of T2 Bacteriophage", 1946 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - "Influenza Virus", May 8-11, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - "Combined Abstract of Tobacco Mosaic Virus and Formaldehyde Studies," Max Lauffer and Marie A. Fischer, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - "Biophysical & Biochemical Characteristics of Viruses", February 24, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - "Hydration of Viruses & Proteins", October 4, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - "Virus Chemistry", December 14, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - "Viruses: Large Molecules or Small Organisms?", February 15, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - "Biophysics Laboratory Demonstration", February 23, 1950 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Seminars, March 17, 1950, March 31, 1950 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - "Blood Lipoproteins and Arteriosclerosis", October 18, 1950 (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - "Biophysical Studies on Viruses", December 13, 1950 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - "Chemical and Physical Properties of Viruses," American Chemical Society Tour, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - "Solvation of Macromolecules", April 4, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - "Kinetics of the Disintigration of Tobacco Mosaic Virus," Lauffer and Schachman, ASC Meeting, September 1951 (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - "Form and Function: A Problem in Biophysics", October 9, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - "X-Ray Studies on Bacteriophage", January 16, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 35)
    - "Pure Versus Applied Science", March 11, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - "Camp Detrick Lectures", May 7, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 37)
    - "Die physikalischen, chemischen, und biologischen Eigenschaften der Viren", December 1, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 38)
    - "Viruses as Physical and Biological Entities," RNS General Science Seminar, October 20, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - "Tobacco Mosaic Virus," ACS Lecture Tour, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 40)
    - "Horizons in Virus Research", 1957 (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - "Living Molecules," WQED TV Program, Max Lauffer and Charles Brinton, Jr., 1957 (Box 7, Folder 42)
    - "The Charge Effect in Sedimentation," Max Lauffer and J.H. Tremaine, Division of Biological Chemistry, ACS Meeting in Miami, April 7, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 43)
    - "Tobacco Mosaic Virus," Radio Script, June 5, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 44)
    - "Physical Characterization of T3 Bacteriophage," ACS Meeting, September 10, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 45)
    - "The Effects of Radiation on Biological Systems," The Society of Nuclear Medicine in Pittsburgh, December 7, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 46)
    - "Frontiers in Virus Research," New York Academy of Medicine, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 47)
    - "Research Prospectives in Nutrition: The Nucleus of the Problem", 1958 (Box 7, Folder 48)
    - "The Polymerization-Depolymerization of Tobacco Mosaic Virus Protein," Max Lauffer, A.T. Ansevin, T.E. Cartwright; Biophysical Society, February 1958 (Box 7, Folder 49)
    - "Living Molecules," American Chemical Society Tour, May 6-9, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 50)
    - "Viruses and Cancer", November 5, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 51)
    - "Anatomy of a Virus," Pittsburgh Award Address, December 11, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 52)
    - "The Morphology of Viruses", October 20, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 53)
    - "The Anatomy of a Virus", October 21, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - "Water, Virus, and Life", December 9, 1963 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - "Endothermic Polymerization of TMV Protein," International Union for Pure and Applied Biophysics: Commission on Molecular Biophysics, June 24-27, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - "Formation of Polymers of Tobacco Mosaic Virus Protein," International Symposium on Molecular Electro-Optics, September 1-4, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Assorted Science Talks, 1968-2002 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - "A Bio-kinetic Process" (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - "Camp Detrick Series: The Effect of Radiation on Living Organisms" (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - "Can Life Be Synthesized?" (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - "Contributions of Virus Research to Chemistry and Physics" (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - "Die Ultrazentrifuge in der Virus-Forshung" (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - "Disintegration of Influenza and Other Viruses" (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - "Disintegration of Viruses" (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - "Electrophoretic Characterization of Biological Entities" (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - "Experimental Methods and Facts Pertaining to the Connection Between Viscosity, Molecular Size, and Molecular Shape" (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - "Hinshelwood Series," Camp Detrick (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - "Hydration" (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - "The Inactivation of Viruses at Extremely High Pressures" (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - "Influenza Virus" (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - "Kinetics of the Inactivation & Destruction of Tobacco Mosaic Virus" (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - "Kinetics of Reactions between Tobacco Mosaic Virus and Formaldehyde" (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - "Methods" (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - "The Origin of the Streaming Potential in Organic Liquids" (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - "Physical & Chemical Characteristics of Viruses" (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - "Physical & Chemical Properties of Viruses" (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - "Physical, Chemical and Biological Properties of Viruses," Theodor Kocher Institute, Germany (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - "Physics and Chemistry of Tobacco Mosaic Virus" (1) (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - "Physics and Chemistry of Tobacco Mosaic Virus" (2) (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - "Physical Properties of Alfalfa Mosaic Virus" (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - "Poliomyelitis Virus" (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - "The Reaction of Tobacco Mosaic Virus Protein with Formaldehyde," Max Lauffer and T.E. Cartwright (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - "The Size and Shape of Tobacco Mosaic Virus Protein Molecules" (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - "The Size and Shape of Viruses" (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - "The Smallest Pathogens" (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - "Ultrafiltration" (Box 8, Folder 34)
    - "Viruses and Human Welfare" (Box 8, Folder 35)
    - "Viruses as Molecules" (Box 8, Folder 36)
    - "Viruses as Organisms" (Box 8, Folder 37)
    - "The Virus Proteins" (Box 8, Folder 38)
    - "Viscosity and Molecular Weight" (Box 8, Folder 39)
  - Religious and Non-Technical Talks, 1946-2000; 2.
    This subseries consists of copies of non-technical lectures on topics such as religion, education, world peace, and nuclear power. It is arranged chronologically and there are undated talks at the end of the subseries.
    - Talks Regarding Church and Religion, 1950-1999 (Box 8, Folder 40)
    - Notecards for Church Talks and Meditations, 1975-1998 (Box 8, Folder 41)
    - "Virus Research," University of Pittsburgh, December 2, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 42)
    - "Atomic Bomb", September 16, 1949, April 23, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 43)
    - "Science and Religion", April 1 & 8, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 44)
    - "Your Stake in Education", October 17, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 45)
    - "Biophysics and Education", April 24, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 46)
    - "Impressions of Science in Europe," Biochemistry Seminar, March 26, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 47)
    - "The Effect of Sponsored Research on the University," AAUP Meeting, February 18, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 48)
    - "The Crucible", April 7, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 49)
    - "United World Federalists Panel Discussion", December 4, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 50)
    - "Careers, Training, and Future in Biophysics," National Biophysics Conference, March 4-6, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 51)
    - "Skeptical Faith," University Service of Worship, February 11, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 52)
    - "How to Influence Children So They Can Get a Higher Education," Franklin Township PTA, February 17, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 53)
    - Dubbing from Nutrition Conference, December 16, 1958 (Box 24, Reel 1)